Guide to the French Government Documents and Political Pamphlets, 1626-1804
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
French government documents and political pamphlets
1626-1804
MS 1006
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
Printed censorship decrees (1626-1789) issued by the Parlement of Paris, provincial Parlements, the Conseil d'Etat du Roi, bishops and archbishops in France, Pope Clemens XI, and others make up the largest part of the French government documents and political pamphlets. Most of the works banned are ecclesiastical. A small amount of political literature and government decrees from the period of the French Revolution and the Napoleonic era are also included.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Decrees Condemning Books, 1626-1789. II. Miscellaneous Political Pamphlets and Government Documents, 1789-1804.
Scope and Contents
The largest part of this collection of printed matter is made up of censorship decrees issued by various government and ecclesiastical bodies between 1626 and 1789. Among those represented are: the Parlement of Paris; provincial Parlements; the king of France; the Conseil d'Etat du Roi; the Paris police (whose decrees were directed as much against the book trade as the individual author); the theological faculty at the Sorbonne; bishops, archbishops and the Pope (in decrees concerning France). Although most of the works falling under the ban are theological, there are also secular works of literature, history and philosophy in the list. Notable among them are the entire works of Voltaire (see the Arrest du Conseil d'Estat du Roy, 1785 Jun 3) and Helvetius' De l'Esprit, (banned in the papal decree of 1759 Jan 31).
The collection also includes a small amount of literature from the period of the French Revolution and some documents issued during the Napoleonic era. One Jugement dated 1792 Jan 24, has a holograph note on the last page reading: "Premier Jugement à mort par du Guillotine. Executé du Avril 1792." Three publications on Voltaire include two describing the ceremonies surrounding the removal of his body to the Pantheon in 1791 and a pamphlet (published in 1781) denouncing his writings to the Parlement of Paris.
The material was organized and annotated by Jeffrey Merrick in 1978.
The papers are divided into two series. Series I contains censorship decrees (1626-1789). Series II is a small collection of political pamphlets and government decrees (1789-1904).
Other Finding Aids
For a listing of books for which censorship decrees were issued, please consult the Banned Books Index.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Censorship -- France; Guillotine; Prohibited books; Europe; France -- History -- Bourbons, 1589-1789; France -- History -- Revolution, 1789-1799; Clement, Pope, XI, 1649-1721; Louis, King of France, XV, 1710-1774; Louis, King of France, XVI, 1754-1793; Helvétius, 1715-1771; Voltaire, 1694-1778
- Decrees Condemning Books, 1626-1789; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the censorship decrees (1626-1789) listed chronologically by the issuing body. As an appendix a copy of the "Listes des Livres Condamnés de 1715 à 1789" from Félix Rocquain, L'Esprit Révolutionaire avant la Révolution (Paris 1878) may be found at the repository. This list gives the full title of each book condemned by the Conseil d'Estat, the Parlement of Paris, by the Châtelet and the Grand Conseil, and can be used in conjunction with our chronological list. Contact a reference librarian for information about this appendix.
  - Paris. Parlement. Arrests de la Cour de Parlement
    - 1680 Apr 3-1769 Feb 10 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 11)
    - 1770 Jul 13-1789 Jun 23 (Box 2, Folder 12 - 16)
  - Paris. Parlement Remonstrances [printed in the Flammarian collection of remonstrances], 1730 October 30, 1737 April 6 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Parisian courts other than the Parlement
    - Chambre des Comptes, 1760 February 23-1787 March 14 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Cour des Aides, 1761 June 23-1785 September 7 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Cour des Monnoies, 1759 December 22, 1771 December 11, 1776 January 27 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Provincial Parlements
    - Aix, 1712 April 18-1771 December 9 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Bordeaux, 1729 September 12 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Bretagne, 1716 November 13-1763 January 31 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Dijon, 1762 June 7 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Douay, 1716 August 6 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Grenoble, 1718 April 7-1781 September 7 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Lorraine et Barrois, 1725 December 31-1786 June 6 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Mans, 1726 January 1?, 1761 August 6 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Metz, 1719 January 17-1775 November 18 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Nantes, 1720 February 10 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Poitiers, 1765 December 10 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Provence, 1718 December 20-1763 February 26 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Rennes
      - 1717 Oct 12, 1733 Mar 28, 1733 May 4
      - 1787 Sep 17 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Rouen, 1718 November 24, 1762 February 12, 1763 March 3 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Toulouse, 1733 April 33-1763 June 18 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Vannes, 1719 January 21, 1719 February 9 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Royal decrees: Declarations and Lettres Patentes, 1699 August 4-1774 March 18 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Arrests du Conseil d'Estat du Roy, 1703 March 5-1789 August 26 (Box 3, Folder 24 - 35)
  - Miscellaneous jurisdictions
    - Assemblée des Cardinaux, Archevêques et Evêques [two printings: Bourges and Rouen], 1714 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Grand Conseil du Roy, 1733 March 17, 1777 October 1 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Sénéchausée de Marseille, 1788 July 30 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Bishops and archbishops [by diocese]
    - Auxerre, 1725 December 20 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Bayeux, 1724 June 17, 1724 September 24 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Beauvais, 1716 December 14 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Carcassone, 1748 February 3 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Chaalons, 1728 November 14 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Embrun, 1732 May 1, 1734 February 15, 1734 June 2? (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Laon, 1731 February 24 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Lodève, 1748 March 26 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Marseille, 1726 January 14-1737 June 15 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Metz, 1729 August 16 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Montauban, 1753 September 21 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Montpellier, 1729 July 3? (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Paris, 1693 August 16-1751 November 18 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Reims, 1716 October 5, 1717 January 4 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Rouen, 1748 April 6 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Soissons, 1719 June 24, 1748 January 7 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Tours, 1747 December 15 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Troyes, 1756 January 6 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Sacrae Facultatis Theologicae Parisiensis [i.e. The Sorbonne], 1682 November 4-1716 October 1 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Paris. Lieutenance de police, 1669 September 10-1777 September 27 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Paris. Chastelet, 1752 November 4-1788 November 21 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Clemens XI, pope, 1649-1721 [papal decrees concerning France]
    - 1703 Mar 17 [2 copies. One printed in Paris. No place on the second] (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - 1713 Sep 8 [2 copies. One printed in Paris, the other in Grenoble] (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - 1749 Sep 20, 1758 Dec 2 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - 1759 Jan 31 [condemnation of Helvetius' De l'Esprit, à Paris, chez Durand] (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Miscellaneous decrees [mostly on ecclesiastical matters], 1656 October-1748 May 2 (Box 4, Folder 44)
- Miscellaneous Political Pamphlets and Government Documents, 1789-1804; Series II
  This series is a miscellaneous collection of government decrees and privately printed pamphlets published between 1789 and 1804.
  - Avis à la Nation Assemblée. Londres, 109 p, 1789 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Mémoire instructif. Remis de la part du Roi au Comité des subsistances des Etats-généraux, par le Directeur général des Finances, [1789] (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Testament de M. Chrétien-François de Lamoignon, Chevalier, Marquis de Bâville, ancien Président à mortier au Parlement de Paris, & ancien Garde-des Sceaux de France: Ecrit de sa main, la surveille de sa mort; & communiqué par le sieur de Lorger, son homme de confiance, [1789] (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Instruction...par ordere du Roi
    - Aux directoires de Départements Sur le Décret de l'Assemblée Nationale, du 16 décembre 179?, sanctionné par Sa Majesté, portant qu'il sera accordé sur les fonds du Trésor public, une somme de Quinze millions, pur subvenir aux déprenses des travaux de secours aui seront établis dans les quatre-vingt-trois Départements, en exécution dudit Décret. Paris, Imprimerie Royale, 1790. 8 p. (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Aux directoires de Départment, Sur la manière de pourvoir au remboursement des frais de la Justice criminelle, & au payement des courses extraordinaires de la Maréchaussée. Paris, Imprimerie Royale, 1790. 8 p. (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Sur la manière d'opèrer les Compensations de la moitié des Quittances de Décimes ou de Capitation payées par les ci-devant Privilégiés: Avec leur Cotisations dans les Rôles de supplément des six derniers mois 1789. Paris, Imprimerie Royale, 1790. 8 p. (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Observations, Sur le Chapitre VIII d'un Imprimé, ayant pour titre LIVRE ROUGE. A Paris, chez Baudouin, Imprimeur de l'Assemblée Nationale. Paris, Imprimerie Royale, 1790. 4 p. Bound with: Etat des Ordonnances...1787 and 1788 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Voltaire
    - Denonciation au Parlement de la souscription pour les oeuvres de Voltaire. n.p., 1781. 15 p. (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Translation de Voltaire à Paris, et détails de la cérémonie qui aura lieu le 4 Juillet. Arrêtés par le Directoire du Département de Paris, sur le rapport de M. Charron, Officier Municipal Commissaire à la Translation. [Paris] Imprimeurs de la Municipalité, [1791]. 37 p. (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Départment de Paris. Ordre du Cortège pour la translation de VOLTAIRE, le Lundi 11 Juillet 1791. Paris, Imprimerie de Ballard, 1791. 3 p. (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Loi. Relative au prétendu Bref du Pape. Donnée à Paris, le 23 Janvier 1791. Arras, De l'Imprimerie de la Ve. de Michel Nicolas, [1791]. 3 p. (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Acte du Corps Législatif...donné à Paris, le 3 Mai 1792, l'an 4e de la Liberté. Beauvai, Imprimerie de P.C.D. Desjardins, 1792. 2 p. (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Acte du Corps Législatif...donné à Paris, le 3 Mai 1792, l'an 4e de la Liberté. Besançon, Imprimerie de Métoyer, 1792. 2 p. (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Acte du Corps Législatif...donné à Paris, le 25 Mai 1792, l'an 4e de la Liberté. Paris, Imprimerie Royale, 1792. 3 p. (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Lettre du Ministre de la Justice, au Commissaire du Roi près le Tribunal criminel du Département de Paris. Paris, L'Imprimerie Royale, 1792 [2 p.] (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Loi. Relative aux Libelles incivique & autre écrits tendant à égarer l'opinion publique. Du 18 Août 1792, l'an quatrième de la Liberté. Paris, Imprimerie Nationale, 1792. 2 p. (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Jugement rendu en dernier ressort, par le III.me Tribunal Criminel...condamne Nicolas-Jacques Pelletier...[24 Janvier 1792]. Paris, chez Quillau, 1792. 4 p. [Holograph note on p. 4: Premier Jugement à mort par du Guillotine. Executé du Avril 1792] (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Jugement rendu par le Tribunal Criminel de Département de Paris...condamne Jean Mury & Daniel Houzel...[17 Avril 1792]. Paris, Imprimerie de Cl.Simon, 1792. 7 p. (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Jugement rendu par le Tribunal Criminel du Departément de Paris,.. condamne ledit Pierre-Severin Hunout...[18 Avril 1792]. [Paris] Imprimerie de Cl. Simon, 1792. 4 p. (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Jugement rendu en dernier ressort, par le IIIme Tribunal Criminel... qui déclare Claude Geoffroy, Prêtre, se disant ci-devant Grand-Vicaire du Diocèse de Dijon, atteint & convaincu d'avoir contribué sciemment à l'exposition & distribution de faux Assignats de cinq livre...[5 Mai 1792] Paris, chez Quillau, 1792. 8 p. (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Jugement rendu par le Tribunal Criminel du Département de Paris...condamne Julien Harry & Louis Darthuys...[16 Mai 1792]. [Paris] Imprimerie C. Simon, 1792. 4 p. (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Mémoire a consulter et consultation pour le sieur Martin Dithurbide...et dame Marie-Joseph Befroy...Paris, Imprimerie de H. J. Jansen, 1792. 6 p. (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Strasbourg. L'Assemblée Générale des Autorités Constituées: La république, une-indivisible ou la mort. Strasbourg, Imprimerie de Phil. J. Dannbach, 1794. 16 p. [At head of title: Séance extraordinaire de l'Assemblée Générale des Autorités Constituées de Strasbourg, convoquée par les citoyens Milhaud et Guyardin Representans du peuple près l'armée du Rhin] (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Rapport fait par les citoyens Calès et Perrin, représentans envoyés, par la Convention nationale, près l'armée des Ardennes; Imprimé par ordre de la Convention Nationale. Paris, Imprimerie Nationale [1795?] (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Malouet, Pierre Victor, baron, 1740-1814
    - Lettre de M. Malouet, député de St. Domingue, à ses commettans. [London, 1798] 8 p. (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Seconde lettre d'un colon de St. Domingue à M. Malouet. Londres, Imprimerie de T. Baylis, 1798. 43 p. (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Troisième lettre d'un colon de St. Domingue à M. Malouet. Londres, Imprimerie de T: Baylis, 1798. 25 p. (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - De l'influence des clubs sur la révolution. [Paris, 1799]. 16 p. (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Arrétés des Consuls...Paris, chez Guillaume, [1800?] (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Decret Imperial...Detail officiel du combat naval qui a eu lieu à Boulogne...[Paris], Imprimerie de Hayez, [1804?] 4 p. (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Mémoire sur les substances. [n.p., after 1789] [on the price of bread] (Box 5, Folder 53)